<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Claustrum regale reseratum, or, The Kinges concealment at Trent published by A.W.</title>
            <author>Wyndham, Anne.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1667</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 54 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 26 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A67220</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W3772</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R34100</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13764605</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13764605</idno>
            <idno type="VID">101712</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A67220)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 101712)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1055:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Claustrum regale reseratum, or, The Kinges concealment at Trent published by A.W.</title>
                  <author>Wyndham, Anne.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>48 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Will. Nott ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1667.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Engraved t.p.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  II, --  King of England, 1630-1685.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Restoration, 1660-1688.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Amanda Flynn</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Amanda Flynn</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="engraved_title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:101712:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:101712:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:101712:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>CLAVSTRVM REGALE RESERATVM or, The Kinges Concealment at Trent, published by A. W.</head>
                  <figDesc>engraved title page border depicting the escape of King Charles II from Parliamentary troops, and his hiding place at Trent.</figDesc>
                  <q>In vmbrâ alarum tuarum sperabo donec transeat iniquitas</q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for Will Nott at the Queens Arms in the Pell:Mell. 1667.</p>
                  <byline>P. Williamson fecit</byline>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:101712:3"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:101712:3"/>
            <head>TO THE QUEEN'S Moſt Excellent MAJESTY.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His little Book having ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained liberty, after a long Impriſonment, to walk a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, proſtrates it ſelf at Your Majeſties feet for patronage and protection. In it Your Majeſty may behold GOD's wonderful Mercy and Providence, in keeping and preſerving our Gracious Soveraign from the hands of His Enemies, when they ſo pleaſed
<pb facs="tcp:101712:4"/> themſelves with the hopes of ſeiſing His Sacred Perſon after the Battel of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> As they had invented and prepared new ways to afflict His Majeſty, ſuch as till then never entred into the hearts of the worst of Tyrants before them. But it pleaſed God to fruſtrate the hopes and deſigns of the Kings Adverſaries, and to reſtore His Majeſty to His Fathers Throne: Which that He may long enjoy with Your Majeſty, in Health, Peace and Happineſs, Is, and ſhall be the prayers of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your MAJESTIE's Moſt obedient, and moſt Faithful Servant, <hi>ANNE WYNDHAM.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:101712:4"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Clauſtrum Regale Reſeratum:</hi> OR, <hi>The KING'S</hi> Concealment AT TRENT.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ow that after the Battel of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> His Sacred Majeſty moſt wonderfully eſcaped the hands of his blood-thirſty Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and (under a Diſguiſe, in the company of M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> 
               <hi>Jane Lane)</hi> ſafely arrived at <hi>Abbots-Leigh</hi> in <hi>Somerſetſhire,</hi> (the ſeat of Sir <hi>George Norton,</hi> lying near to the City of <hi>Briſtol)</hi> hath been fully publiſhed unto the World. His Majeſtie's Journey from thence to the houſe of Colonel <hi>Francis Wyndham</hi> at <hi>Trent</hi> in the ſame County, his Stay there, his En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:101712:5"/> (though fruſtrate) to get over into <hi>France,</hi> his Return to <hi>Trent,</hi> his final De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture thence in order to his happy Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portation, are the ſubject of this preſent Relation. A Story, in which the Conſtel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations of Providence are ſo refulgent, that their light is ſufficient to confute all the Atheiſts of the world, and to enforce all perſons (whoſe faculties are not pertina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly depraved) to acknowledge a watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Eye of GOD from above, looking upon all Actions of Men here below, making even the moſt wicked ſubſervient to his juſt and glorious deſigns. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, whatſoever the Antients fabled of <hi>Gyges's</hi> Ring, by which he could render himſelf Inviſible, or the Poets fancied of their Gods, who uſually carried their chief Favourites in the Clouds, and by drawing thoſe aerial Curtains, did ſo conceal them, that they were heard and ſeen of none, whilſt they both heard and ſaw others, is here moſt certainly verified. For, the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty ſo cloſely covered the King with the wing of his Protection, and ſo clouded the Underſtanding of his cruel Enemies,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:101712:5"/> that the moſt piercing Eye of Malice could not ſee, nor the moſt Barbarouſly-bloody Hand offer Violence to his Sacred Perſon: God ſmiting his purſuers (as once he did the <hi>Sodomites)</hi> with blindneſs, who with as much eagerneſs ſought to ſacrifice the Lords Anointed to their fury, as the other did to proſtitute the Angels to their luſt.</p>
            <p>But before the ſeveral Particulars of this Story are laid open, two Queſtions (eaſily foreſeen) which will be readily asked by every Reader, call for an Anſwer. The one is, Why this Relation ſo much expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſo much longed for, has been kept up all this while from publick view? And the other, How it comes to paſs, that now it takes the liberty to walk abroad? Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the firſt, it muſt be known, that a Narrative of theſe Paſſages was (by eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial command from his Majeſty) written by the Colonels own hand, immediately after the Kings return into <hi>England;</hi> which (being preſented to his Majeſty) was laid up in his Royal Cabinet, there to reſt for ſome time, it being the Kings pleaſure (for
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:101712:6"/> reaſons beſt known to his Sacred ſelf) that it ſhould not then be publiſhed.</p>
            <p>And as his Majeſties command to keep it private, is a ſatisfactory anſwer to the firſt; ſo, his licence now obtained that it might travel abroad, may ſufficiently reſolve the ſecond queſtion. But beſides this, many prevalent reaſons there are, which plead for a publication; the chief of which are briefly theſe. That the implacable Enemies of this Crown may be for ever ſilenced and aſhamed; who having neither Law, nor Religion to patronize their unjuſt under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takings, conſtrued a bare Permiſſion, to be a Divine Approbation of their Actions; and (taking the Almighty to be ſuch a one as themſelves) blaſphemouſly entitled God to be the Author of all their wickedneſs. But the arm of God ſtretched out from heaven to the reſcue of the King, cutting off the clue of their Succeſs, even then when they thought they had ſpun up their thred, hath not left them ſo much as an apron of fig-leaves to cover the nakedneſs of their moſt ſhameful proceedings.</p>
            <p>The next is, That the Truth of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:101712:6"/> Eſcape (being minced by ſome, miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken by others, and not fully ſet forth by any) might appear in its native beauty and ſplendor: That as every duſt of gold is gold, and every ray of light is light; ſo every jot and title of Truth being Truth, not one grain of the treaſure, nor one beam of the luſtre of this Story might be loſt or clouded; it being ſo rare, ſo excellent, that aged Time out of all the Archives of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity can hardly produce a Parallel. Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularly admirable indeed it is, if we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the Circumſtances and Actors. The Colonel (who chiefly deſigned, and moved in this great Affair) could not have had the freedom to have ſerved his Majeſty, had he not been a Priſoner; his very Confinement giving him both a liberty, and protection to act. For, coming home from <hi>Weymouth</hi> upon his Parole, he had the opportunity to travel freely and ſafely, without fear of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtopped, and taken up: And being newly removed from <hi>Sherborne</hi> to <hi>Trent,</hi> the jealous eye of <hi>Somerſetſhire</hi> Potentates had ſcarce then found him out, whoſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>levolent Aſpect afterwards ſeldom ſuffered
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:101712:7"/> him to live at home, and too too often fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed his houſe with very unwelcom gueſts. Others, who contributed their aſſiſtance, were perſons of both ſexes, and of very dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent conditions and qualities: And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though their endeavours often proved ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsleſs, though they received diſcourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments on one hand, were terrified with threats on the other; That a ſeal of ſilence ſhould be imprinted upon the lips of Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, who are become proverbial for their garrulity; That faithfulneſs and conſtancie ſhould guard the hearts of Servants, who are uſually corrupted with rewards or af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frighted with puniſhments; That neither Hope nor Fear (moſt powerful paſſions, heightned by Capital animadverſions pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed againſt All that ſhould conceal, and large Remunerations promiſed to ſuch as ſhould diſcover the King) could work no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing upon any ſingle perſon, ſo as to remove him or her from their reſpective duty, but that all ſhould ſo harmoniouſly concenter, both in the Deſign, and alſo afterward keep themſelves ſo long cloſe ſhut up under the lock of ſecrecy, that nothing could be diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:101712:7"/> by the moſt exquiſite art and cunning, till the bleſſed Reſtauration of his Majeſty to his glorious Throne, ſo filled their hearts with joy, that it broke open the door of their lips, and let their tongue looſe to tell this Miracle to the amazed World, would (were not the Perſons yet alive, and the Story freſh in memory) rarifie it into a Romance.</p>
            <p>The reproaches and ſcandals, by which ſome envious perſons have ſought to dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh and vilifie the faithful ſervices, which the Colonel out of the integrity of his ſoul performed unto his Majeſty, ſhall not here be mentioned: Becauſe by taking up dirt to beſpatter him, they defile their own hands, and the gun they level at his Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, recoils to the wounding of their own.</p>
            <p>Theſe things thus premiſed, by way of Introduction, open the Gate, through which you may enter, and in the enſuing Pages (as in ſeveral Tables) take a full view of the Particulars.</p>
            <p>The Diſguiſe his Majeſty put on, ſecured him from the Cruelty of his Enemies; but
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:101712:8"/> could not altogether hide him from the pry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing eyes of his dutiful Subjects. For in the time of his ſtay at <hi>Leigh,</hi> one <hi>John Pope</hi> (then Butler to Sir <hi>George Norton,</hi> but for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly a Soldier for the King in the Weſt) through all thoſe clouds eſpied the moſt Illuſtrious Perſon of the King. With him his Majeſty (after he ſaw himſelf diſcovered) was pleaſed familiarly to diſcourſe; And ſpeaking of the great Sufferings of very many of his Friends in the Weſtern parts, (moſt whereof were well known to <hi>Pope)</hi> his Majeſty enquired if he knew Colonel <hi>Francis Wyndham,</hi> who (in the time of the late Wars) was Governor of <hi>Dunſter-Caſtle?</hi> Very well, Sir, anſwered <hi>Pope.</hi> The King then demanding what was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of him? <hi>Pope</hi> replies, That the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonel had married M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> 
               <hi>Anne Gerard,</hi> one of the daughters and heireſſes of <hi>Thomas Gerard</hi> Esq; late of <hi>Trent</hi> in <hi>Somerſetſhire,</hi> and that he had newly brought thither his Mother (the Lady <hi>Wyndham)</hi> his Wife and family, and that he believed the Colonel intended there to reſide and live. His Majeſty having received this intelligence concerning the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:101712:8"/> Colonel, together with an exact information of the ſcituation of <hi>Trent,</hi> ſought an op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to ſpeak with M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> 
               <hi>Lane,</hi> (from whom, the better to conceal himſelf, he then kept at a diſtance) and by means of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Laſſels</hi> (who accompanied the King in this journey) obteining his deſire, his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty with much contentment imparted to M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> 
               <hi>Lane</hi> what <hi>Pope</hi> had informed him con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Colonel <hi>Wyndham,</hi> and his habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; telling her withall, That if ſhe could bring him thither, he ſhould not much doubt of his ſafety.</p>
            <p>In this very point of time comes the Lord <hi>Henry Wilmot</hi> (ſince Earl of <hi>Rocheſter)</hi> from <hi>Dirham</hi> in <hi>Glouceſterſhire</hi> (the ſeat of <hi>John Winter</hi> Esq; a perſon of known loyalty and integrity) to <hi>Leigh.</hi> My Lord had attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Majeſty in his paſſage Weſtward, and on Friday morning <hi>(September</hi> the 13.) met accidentally Captain <hi>Thomas Abington</hi> of <hi>Dowdſwell</hi> in the County of <hi>Glouceſter,</hi> at <hi>Pinbury</hi> Park; and being known by the Captain, (who had ſerved under his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip in the Wars) was that night by him conducted to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Winter's,</hi> from whom his
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:101712:9"/> Lordſhip (as he hath often ſince acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged) received great Civilities. M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> 
               <hi>Lane</hi> preſently reveals to the Lord <hi>Wilmot</hi> the Kings reſolution to remove to <hi>Trent:</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon my Lord demanded of <hi>Henry Rogers</hi> (M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Winter's</hi> ſervant, and his Lordſhips guide from <hi>Dirham</hi> to <hi>Leigh)</hi> whether he knew <hi>Trent?</hi> He anſwered, That Colonel <hi>Wyndham</hi> and his Maſter had married two Siſters, and that he had often waited on his Maſter thither. Theſe things ſo happily concurring, his Majeſty commanded the Lord <hi>Wilmot</hi> to haſte to <hi>Trent,</hi> and to aſcertain the Colonel of his ſpeedy Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach.</p>
            <p>His Lordſhip took leave, and continuing <hi>Rogers</hi> for his guide, with one <hi>Robert Swan,</hi> arrived at <hi>Trent</hi> the ſixteenth of <hi>September. Rogers</hi> was ſent in forthwith to the Colonel to acquaint him, that a Gentleman a friend of his, deſired the favour of him, that he would pleaſe to ſtep forth and ſpeak with him. The Colonel enquiring of <hi>Rogers,</hi> whether he knew the Gentleman or his buſineſs? anſwered, No, he underſtood nothing at all, but only that he was called
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:101712:9"/> by the name of <hi>Mr. Morton.</hi> Then without further diſcourſe the Colonel came forth, and found the Gentleman walking near the Stable; whom as ſoon as he approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, (although it was ſomewhat dark) he ſaluted by the Title of <hi>My Lord Wilmot.</hi> His Lordſhip ſeemed to wonder that he ſhould be known, but it was nothing ſtrange, conſidering the Colonels former acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance with him, being one of the firſt that engaged under his Command, in his late Majeſties ſervice: Beſides, his Lordſhip was not in the leaſt altered, except a Hawk on his fiſt, and a Lure by his ſide might paſs for a Diſguiſe. This Confidence of his Lordſhip really begat admiration in the Colonel, calling to mind the great danger he was in, and whoſe Harbinger he was; For he advertiſed the Colonel, that the King himſelf was on his way to <hi>Trent,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending that very night to lodge at <hi>Caſtle-Cary</hi> (a Town ſix miles thence) hoping by Gods aſſiſtance, to be with him about ten of the clock next morning.</p>
            <p>At this joyful news the Colonel was tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported, (there having run a report, that his
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:101712:10"/> Majeſty was ſlain in the Fight at <hi>Worceſter)</hi> and giving God thanks for his wonderful mercy, he aſſured his Lordſhip, <hi>That for his Majeſties preſervation he would value neither his life, family nor fortune, and would never injure his Majeſties confidence of him; Not doubting, but that God who had led his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty through the midſt of ſuch inexpreſſible dangers, would deliver him from all thoſe barbarous threats, and bloody intentions of his Enemies.</hi> With theſe and ſuch like ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, the Colonel brought the Lord <hi>Wilmot</hi> into his parlour, where he received an exact account of his Majeſties condition, and preſent affairs.</p>
            <p>Next morning, the Colonel found it neceſſary to acquaint the Lady <hi>Wyndham</hi> his mother, and alſo his own Lady, with the particulars the Lord <hi>Wilmot</hi> had over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night imparted to him, concerning the King. The relation he gave them, did not (through the weakneſs of their ſex) bring upon them any womaniſh paſſion, but ſurprized with joy, they moſt cheerfully reſolve (without the leaſt ſhew of fear) to hazard all, for the ſafety of the King. And ſo (begging Gods
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:101712:10"/> bleſſing upon their future endeavours) they contrive how his Majeſty might be brought into the houſe, without any ſuſpition to their family, conſiſting of above twenty perſons. Among them therefore, <hi>M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Julian Coningsby</hi> (the Lady <hi>Wyndham's</hi> Neece) <hi>Elianor Withers, Joan Halſenoth,</hi> and <hi>Henry Peters</hi> (whoſe loy alty to the King, and fidelity to themſelves, they had ſufficiently experienced) are made privy to their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign. Next they conſider what Chambers are fitteſt for his Majeſties reception. Four are made choice of; amongſt which, the Lady <hi>Wyndham</hi>'s was counted moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient for the day-time, where the ſervants might wait with moſt freedom upon his Majeſty. Then a ſafe place is provided to retreat unto, in caſe of ſearch, or imminent danger: And laſtly, Employments are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned to remove all others out of the way at the inſtant of his Majeſties arrival. All which after a while, anſwered their deſires, even beyond their expectation.</p>
            <p>Between nine and ten the next morning, the Colonel and his Lady walking towards the fields adjoining to the houſe, eſpied the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:101712:11"/> King riding before <hi>M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Lane,</hi> and <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Laſſels</hi> in their company. Aſſoon as his Majeſty came near the Colonel, He called to him, <hi>Frank, Frank <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> how doſt thou do?</hi> By which gracious pleaſance the Colonel per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, that though his Majeſties habit and countenance were much changed, yet his Heroick ſpirit was the ſame, and his mind immutable. The Colonel (to avoid the jealous eyes of ſome neighbours) inſtantly conveyed the King and <hi>M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Lane</hi> into the Lady <hi>Wyndham's</hi> Chamber, where the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of Joy and Sorrow did a while combat in them, who beheld his Sacred Perſon: For what loyal Eye could look upon ſo Glorious a Prince thus eclypſed, and not pay unto him the homage of tears? But the conſideration of his Majeſties ſafety, the gracious words of his own mouth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futing the ſad reports of his untimely death, together with the hope of his future pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, ſoon dried them up. In al ſhort time the Colonel brought the Lord <hi>Wilmot</hi> to the King, and then the Ladies withdrew into the Parlour, having firſt agreed to call <hi>M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Lane</hi> Couſin, and to entertain her with
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:101712:11"/> the ſame familiarity as if ſhe had been their near Relation. That day ſhe ſtayed at <hi>Trent,</hi> and the next morning early M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Laſſels</hi> and ſhe departed.</p>
            <p>His Majeſty, after he had refreſhed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, commanded the Colonel in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the Lord <hi>Wilmot,</hi> to propoſe, What way he thought moſt probable for his Eſcape into <hi>France;</hi> for thither he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired with all ſpeed to be tranſported. The Colonel (the King giving him this oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity) entertained and encouraged his Majeſty with this remarkable paſſage of Sir <hi>Thomas Wyndham</hi> (his Father) <hi>Who, not long before his death [in the Year</hi> 1636] <hi>called unto him his five Sons, (having not ſeen them together in ſome years before) and diſcourſed unto us</hi> [ſaid he] <hi>of the long Peace and Proſperity this Kingdom had enjoyed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der its Three laſt Glorious Monarchs: Of the the many Miſeries and Calamities which lay ſore upon our Anceſtors, by the ſeveral Inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions and Conqueſts of Forein Nations, and likewiſe by Inteſtine Inſurrections and Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions. And notwithſtanding the ſtrange mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations and Changes in</hi> England, <hi>He ſhewed,</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:101712:12"/> 
               <hi>how it pleaſed God in love to our Nation to preſerve an undoubted Succeſſion of Kings, to ſit in the Regal Throne. He mentioned the healing Conjunction of the two Houſes of</hi> York <hi>and</hi> Lancaſter, <hi>and the bleſſed <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion of the two Crowns of</hi> England <hi>and</hi> Scotland, <hi>ſtopping up thoſe fountains of Blood, which by National feuds and quarrels kept open, had like to have drowned the whole Iſland. He ſaid, he feared the beautiful garment of Peace would ſhortly be torn in pieces through the Neglect of Magiſtrates, the general Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of manners, and the prevalence of a Puritanical faction, which (if not prevented) would undermine the very pillars of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. My ſons! We have hitherto ſeen ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rene and quiet Times: but now prepare your ſelves for cloudy and troubleſom. I command you to honour and obey our Gracious Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign, and in all times to adhere to the Crown; and though the Crown ſhould hang upon a Buſh, I charge you forſake it not. Theſe words being ſpoken with much earneſtneſs, both in geſture and manner extraordinary, he aroſe from his chair, and left us in a deep conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation what the meaning ſhould be of—</hi>The
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:101712:12"/> Crown hanging upon a Buſh. <hi>Theſe words, Sir,</hi> (ſaid the Colonel) <hi>made ſo firm an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion in all our breaſts, that the many af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions of theſe ſad Times cannot raze out their undelible characters. Certainly theſe are the days which my Father pointed out in that Expreſsion: And I doubt not, God hath brought me through ſo many dangers, that I might ſhew my ſelf both a dutiful Son, and a loyal Subject, in faithfully endeavouring to ſerve your Sacred Majeſty, in this your greateſt Diſtreſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After this Rehearſal, the Colonel (in obedience to his Majeſties command) told the King, That Sir <hi>John Strangways</hi> (who had given many teſtimonies of his loyalty, having two Sons, both of them Colonels for his Royal Father) lived but four miles from <hi>Trent;</hi> That he was a perſon of great fortune and intereſt in <hi>Dorſetſhire,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ſuppoſed that either Sir <hi>John,</hi> or his Sons, might be ſerviceable to his Majeſties occaſions. The King, in proſecution of this propoſal, commanded the Colonel to wait on them; and accordingly the next morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he went over to <hi>Melbury;</hi> the place
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:101712:13"/> where Sir <hi>John</hi> dwelt. No ſooner was he come thither, but he met with Colonel <hi>Giles Strangways,</hi> and after uſual ſalutations, they walked into the Park adjoyning to the houſe, where Colonel <hi>Wyndham</hi> imparted the reaſon and end of his preſent Viſit. Colonel <hi>Strangways</hi> his anſwer was, That he was infinitely grieved, becauſe he was not able to ſerve his Majeſty in procuring a Veſſel according to expectation; That he knew not any one Maſter of a Ship, or ſo much as one Mariner that he could truſt: All that were formerly of his acquaintance in <hi>Weymouth,</hi> being for their loyalty baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and gone beyond the ſea; and in <hi>Pool</hi> and <hi>Lime</hi> he was a meer ſtranger, having not one Confident in either. A hundred pounds in Gold he delivered to Colonel <hi>Wyndham,</hi> to preſent to the King; which at his return, by command was depoſited in the hands of the Lord <hi>Wilmot,</hi> for his Majeſties uſe.</p>
            <p>About this time the Forces under <hi>Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well</hi> were retreated from <hi>Worceſter</hi> into the ſeveral Quarters of the Country; ſome of which coming to <hi>Trent,</hi> proclaimed the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:101712:13"/> Overthrow of the Kings Army, and the Death of the King, giving out that he was certainly killed; And one of them affirmed that he ſaw him dead, and that he was buried among the reſt of the ſlain, no injury being offered to his body, becauſe he was a Vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant Soldier, and a Gallant man. This wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come News ſo tickled the Sectaries, that they could not hold from expreſſing their joy by making Bonfires, firing of Guns, Drinking, and other jollities: And for a cloſe of all, to the Church they muſt, and there ring the Kings knell. Theſe rude Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagancies moved not his Majeſty at all, but onely (as if he were more troubled for their madneſs, than his own misfortune) to this moſt Chriſtian and compaſſionate Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, <hi>Alas poor people!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now though the King valued not the menaces of his proud Enemies, being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident they could do him no hurt; yet he neglected not to try the faithfulneſs of his Friends to convey him out of their reach. Thus the former deſign proving unſucceſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and all hope of Transfretation that way being laid aſide, the Colonel acquainted
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:101712:14"/> his Majeſty, that one Captain <hi>William El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſden</hi> of <hi>Lime</hi> (formerly well known unto him) with his Brother <hi>John Elleſden,</hi> (by means of Colonel <hi>Bullen Reymes</hi> of <hi>Wadden</hi> in <hi>Dorſetſhine)</hi> had conveyed over into <hi>France,</hi> Sir <hi>John Berkley</hi> (now Lord <hi>Berkley)</hi> in a time of danger. To this Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain therefore his Majeſty ſends the Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel, who lodging at his houſe in <hi>Lime,</hi> took an opportunity to tell him, That the Lord <hi>Wilmot</hi> had made his eſcape from <hi>Worceſter;</hi> that he lay privately near to him; and that his Lordſhip had earneſtly ſolicited him to uſe his utmoſt endeavours to ſecure him from the hands of the purſuers. To this purpoſe he was come to town, and aſſured the Captain, if he would joyn in this affair, his courteſie ſhould never be forgotten. The Captain very cordially embraced the moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and went with the Colonel to <hi>Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth</hi> (a little place near <hi>Lime)</hi> where at an Inne, he brought to him a Tenant of his, one <hi>Stephen Limbry,</hi> aſſuring the Colonel that he was a right honeſt man, and a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Royaliſt. With this <hi>Limbry</hi> Colonel <hi>Wyndham</hi> treated under the name of Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:101712:14"/> 
               <hi>Norris,</hi> and agreed with him to tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port himſelf and three or four friends into <hi>France.</hi> The conditions of their Agreement were; That before the two and twentieth day of that inſtant <hi>September, Limbry</hi> ſhould bring his Veſſel into <hi>Charmouth-Road,</hi> and on the ſaid two and twentieth, in the night ſhould receive the Colonel and his company into his Long-boat from the Beach near <hi>Charmouth,</hi> from thence carry them to his Ship, and ſo land them ſafe in <hi>France.</hi> This the Colonel conjured <hi>Limbry</hi> to perform with all ſecreſie, becauſe all the Paſſengers were of the Royal party, and intended to be ſhipped without leave, to avoid ſuch Oaths and Engagements, which otherwiſe would be forced upon them: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Privacie in this tranſaction would free him from Danger, and themſelves from Trouble, the true cauſe why they ſo earneſtly thirſted (for ſome time) to leave their native Country. <hi>Limbry's</hi> Salary was Sixty pounds, which the Captain engaged to pay at his return from <hi>France,</hi> upon ſight of a Certificate under the Paſſengers hands of their landing there. To the performance
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:101712:15"/> of theſe Covenants, <hi>Limbry</hi> with many vows and proteſtations obliging himſelf, the Colonel with much ſatisfaction, and ſpeed came back to his Majeſty and the Lord <hi>Wilmot</hi> to <hi>Trent,</hi> who at the narrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of theſe paſſages expreſſed no ſmall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment.</p>
            <p>The buſineſs being thus far ſucceſsfully laid, the King conſults how it might be prudentially managed, that ſo there might be no miſcarriage in the proſecution. Neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary it was that his Majeſty and all his At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendants (contrary to the uſe of Travellers) ſhould ſit up all the night in the Inne at <hi>Charmouth;</hi> that they ought to have the command of the houſe, to go in and out at pleaſure, the Tide not ſerving till twelve at night. To remove therefore all ſuſpicion and Inconveniencies, this Expedient was found out.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Henry Peters</hi> (Colonel <hi>Wyndham's</hi> ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant) was ſent to <hi>Charmouth</hi> Inne, who in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viting the Hoſteſs to drink a glaſs of wine, told her, That he ſerved a very gallant Maſter, who had long moſt affectionately loved a Lady in <hi>Devon,</hi> and had the happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:101712:15"/> to be well beloved by her; and though her Equal in birth and fortune, yet ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equal was his fate, that by no means could he obtain her Friends conſent: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it was agreed between them, that he ſhould carry her thence, and marry her among his own Allies. And for this purpoſe his Maſter had ſent him to deſire her to keep the beſt Chambers for him, intending to be at her houſe upon the two and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth day of that moneth in the evening; where he reſolved not to lodge, but only to refreſh himſelf and friends, and ſo travel on either that night, or very early next morning. With this Love-ſtory (thus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trived and acted) together with a Preſent delivered by <hi>Peters</hi> from his Maſter, the Hoſteſs was ſo well pleaſed, that ſhe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed him, her houſe and ſervants ſhould be at his Maſters command. All which ſhe very juſtly performed.</p>
            <p>When the day appointed for his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties journey to <hi>Charmouth</hi> was come, he was pleaſed to ride before M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> 
               <hi>Julian Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningsby</hi> (the Lady <hi>Wyndham's</hi> Neece) as formerly before M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> 
               <hi>Lane:</hi> The Colonel
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:101712:16"/> was his Majeſties Guide, whilſt the Lord <hi>Wilmot</hi> with <hi>Peters</hi> kept at a convenient diſtance, that they might not ſeem to be all of one company.</p>
            <p>In this manner travelling, they were time<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly met by Captain <hi>Eleſden,</hi> and by him conducted to a private houſe of his Brothers among the hills near <hi>Charmouth.</hi> There his Majeſty was pleaſed to diſcover himſelf to the Captain, and to give him a piece of forein Gold, in which in his ſolitary hours he made a hole to put a ribbin in. Many like pieces his Majeſty vouchſafed the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonel and his Lady, to be kept as Records of his Majeſties favour, and of their own fidelity to his moſt Sacred Perſon in the day of his greateſt Trial. All which they have moſt thankfully treaſured up as the chiefeſt Jewels of their Family.</p>
            <p>This Royal Company from thence came to the Inne at <hi>Charmouth,</hi> a little after night; where Captain <hi>Eleſden</hi> ſolemnly engaging to ſee the Maſter of the ſhip ready, (the wind blowing then fair for <hi>France)</hi> took leave of his Majeſty. About an hour after came <hi>Limbry</hi> to the Inne, and aſſured the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:101712:16"/> Colonel all things were prepared, and that about midnight his Long-boat ſhould wait at the place appointed. The ſet hour draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nigh, the Colonel with <hi>Peters</hi> went to the Sea-ſide (leaving his Majeſty and the Lord <hi>Wilmot</hi> in a poſture to come away upon call) where they remained all night expecting; but ſeeing no Long-boat, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hearing any meſſage from the maſter of the ſhip, at the break of day the Colonel returns to the Inne, and beſeeches the King and the Lord <hi>Wilmot</hi> to haſte from thence. His Majeſty was intreated; but the Lord <hi>Wilmot</hi> was deſirous to ſtay behind a little, promiſing to follow the King to <hi>Bridport,</hi> where his Majeſty intended to make a halt for him.</p>
            <p>When the King was gone, the Lord <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mot</hi> ſent <hi>Peters</hi> into <hi>Lime,</hi> to demand of Captain <hi>Eleſden</hi> the reaſon why <hi>Limbry</hi> broke his promiſe, and forfeited his word? He ſeemed much ſurpriſed with this meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, and ſaid, He knew no reaſon, except it being Fair-day, the Seamen were drunk in taking their Farewell; and withall ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed his Lordſhip to be gone, becauſe his
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:101712:17"/> ſtay there could not be ſafe. But ſince that, <hi>Limbry</hi> himſelf hath given this account un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his own hand:—</p>
            <p>That according to an Agreement made at <hi>Charmouth, September</hi> the 19. 1651. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt himſelf and one Captain <hi>Norris,</hi> (ſince known to be Colonel <hi>Francis Wyndham)</hi> he put forth his Ship beyond the <hi>Cobs-mouth</hi> into <hi>Charmouth-rode,</hi> where his ſervants on the 22. of the ſame moneth were all ready in her, waiting his coming; That he going to his houſe about ten that night, for linen to carry with him, was unexpectedly locked into a chamber by his Wife, to whom he had a little before revealed his intended Voyage with ſome Paſſengers into <hi>France,</hi> for whoſe Tranſportation, at his return, he was to receive a conſiderable ſum of money from Captain <hi>Eleſden.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This woman (it ſeems) was frighted into a panick fear by that dreadful Proclamation (of the tenth of <hi>September)</hi> ſet out by the Men of <hi>Weſtminiſter,</hi> and publiſhed that day at <hi>Lime.</hi> In this, a heavy Penalty was thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred out againſt all that ſhould conceal the King, or any of his party who were at <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:101712:17"/> Fight; and a Reward of a Thouſand pounds promiſed to any that ſhould betray him. She, apprehending the Perſons her husband engaged to carry over to be Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aliſts, reſolved to ſecure him from danger, by making him a Priſoner in his own cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber. All the perſwaſions he uſed for his li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, were in vain: For the more he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated, the more her violent paſſion in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed, breaking forth into ſuch clamors and lamentations, that he feared if he ſhould any longer contend, both himſelf and the Gentlemen he promiſed to tranſport, would be caſt away in this ſtorm, without ever go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Sea.</p>
            <p>Thus a Deſign in a buſineſs of the higheſt nature, carried on with induſtry and pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, even to the very laſt, ſtill promiſing full hope of a happy production, by one mans ſingle whiſper (the bane of Action) proved abortive. For no doubt, had <hi>Lim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bry</hi> kept his counſel, he had gained the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of Conveying over his Majeſty; of whoſe Noble Courage and Vertue, God was pleaſed to make yet farther trial, as the ſequel will inform.</p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:101712:18"/>
            <p> The King paſſing on upon <hi>London</hi> Road from <hi>Charmouth,</hi> met many travellers, among whom was one of his Fathers ſervants, well known both to his Majeſty and the Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel; who were very well pleaſed that he was not guilty of ſo much Civility, as to give either of them the complement of a Salutation. As they drew near to <hi>Bridport,</hi> the Colonel riding a little before, and entring the town, perceived it full of Soldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers: whereupon ſtopping his horſe till the King came up, he inreated his Majeſty to keep on, and by no means to put himſelf into the mouth of them, who gaped gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily after his deſtruction. Nevertheleſs, the King having engaged to the Lord <hi>Wilmot</hi> to expect him there, (without the leaſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of danger) rode into the <hi>George,</hi> and alighting in the Court, was forced to ſtay there, and in the Stable, near half an hour, before the Colonel could procure a Chamber. All this while his bloody Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies were his onely Companions, with whom he diſcourſed freely without fear, and learned from them their intended Voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age for <hi>Jerſey</hi> and <hi>Guernſey,</hi> and their
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:101712:18"/> Deſign upon thoſe Iſlands. Here may you ſee the Purſuers overtaken, and the bittereſt of Enemies friendly diſcourſing with Him, whoſe utter Ruine they accounted would compleat their Happineſs. He that ſate in Heaven certainly laughed them to ſcorn, and by the interpoſition of his mighty Arm eclypſed their glory, and by his admirable Wiſdom reproved and confuted their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice againſt the King, and their blaſphemies againſt Heaven.</p>
            <p>No ſooner had the King withdrawn him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf from this dangerous Company into a Chamber (with much difficulty obtained) but <hi>M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Coningsby</hi> eſpied <hi>Peters</hi> riding into the Inne. He (being beckned up) acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Majeſty, that the Lord <hi>Wilmot</hi> hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly petitioned him to make haſte out of that place, and to overtake him ſlowly paſſing on the road, and waiting his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties coming. Preſently upon the diſmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of <hi>Peters,</hi> the King having taken ſome ſmall repaſt, not far from the Town joyned in company again with the Lord <hi>Wilmot,</hi> and diſcourſing of the ſeveral Adventures of that hopeful, and (as it fell out) moſt
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:101712:19"/> perilous Journey, concluded that <hi>London-Road</hi> was very unſafe, and therefore re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to follow the next Turning which might probably lead towards <hi>Yeavill</hi> or <hi>Sherborn,</hi> neither of which is computed to be above two miles diſtant from <hi>Trent.</hi> Providence (the beſt of Guides) directed theſe Strangers (for ſo they were all to thoſe parts) to a way, which after many hours travel brought them into a Village, in which was a ſmall Inne for entertainment. This entred theſe maſqued Travellers, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire where they were. And to this purpoſe calling for ſome Beer, the Hoſt of the houſe (one <hi>Rice Jones)</hi> came forth, and informed them that the place was called <hi>Broadwinſor.</hi> The Colonel knew the Innkeeper and his wife to be very honeſt, loyal perſons, and that for their fidelity to the King and his party, they had (according to their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition) undergone their ſhare of troubles. The King underſtanding the affection of the people, reſolves to lodge in the houſe that night, it being already ſomwhat dark, and his Majeſty and Company ſufficiently wearied with their former nights watching,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:101712:19"/> and that days travel. The Colonel (while the horſes were put up) deſired Mr. <hi>Jones</hi> to ſhew him the moſt private rooms; the reaſon he gave was, Becauſe his Brother-in-law Colonel <hi>Reymes</hi> (whom the Lord <hi>Wilmot</hi> perſonated) had been a long time impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as well as himſelf; That they had late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obtained their Paroles, and to be ſeen together ſo far from their homes, might create new jealouſies, and ſo conſequently cruſh them with new troubles. The good Hoſt upon this brought them up into the higheſt chambers, where Privateneſs recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſed the meanneſs of the Accommoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the pleaſantneſs of the Hoſt (a merry fellow) allayed and mitigated the wearineſs of the Gueſts. Now the face of things began to ſmile, which all the day and night preceding looked ſo louring and ill-favoured. But this ſhort Calm was on a ſudden interrupted by a violent Storm. For in comes the Conſtable with almoſt Forty Soldiers to be billeted that very night in the Inne: All the lower Receptacles were thronged up with this unexpected Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany; ſo that the King was in a manner
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:101712:20"/> beſieged, there being no paſſage from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove, but through thoſe ſuſpected Guards. Thus every place brought forth its troubles, and every period of time diſcloſed freſh dangers! Shortly after the Soldiers had taken up their Quarters, a Woman in their company fell in labour in the Kitchin. The pangs ſhe endured, made the Inhabitants of that place very ill at eaſe, fearing leſt the whole Pariſh ſhould become the reputed Father, and be enforced to keep the Child. To avoid this charge, the chiefeſt of the Pariſh poſt to the Inne, between whom and the Soldiers aroſe a very hot conflict con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning proviſion to be made for the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and the infant. This diſpute continued till ſuch time as (according to orders) they were to march to the Sea-ſide. This quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relſom Goſſipping was a moſt ſeaſonable diverſion, exerciſing the minds of thoſe troubleſom Fellows, who otherwiſe were likely to have proved too too inquiſitive after the Gueſts in the houſe; the ſad con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences of which, every loyal heart trembles to think on.</p>
            <p>Surely we cannot, except we wilfully
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:101712:20"/> ſhut our own eyes) but clearly ſee, and with all reverence and thankfulneſs adore the Divine Goodneſs for his Majeſties ſignal Deliverances in this Voyage. Eſpecially if looking back upon <hi>Charmouth,</hi> we conſider the dangers that threatned him, occaſioned by the Lord <hi>Wilmot's</hi> ſhort ſtay there, after the Kings departure. For one <hi>Hamnet</hi> a Smith, being called to ſhoe his Lordſhips horſe, ſaid, He well knew by the faſhion of the ſhoes, that they were never ſet in the Weſt, but in the North. The Hoſtler (a bird of the ſame feather) hearing this, began to tell what Company had been there, how they ſate up, and kept their horſes ſadled all the night; and from hence they conclude, That either the King, or ſome Great Perſons had certainly been at the Inne. The Hoſtler (whoſe heart was ſoured againſt the King) runs preſently to one <hi>Weſtley</hi> (of the ſame leaven) then Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of <hi>Charmouth,</hi> to inform him of theſe Paſſages, and to ask counſel what was to be done. This <hi>Weſtley</hi> was at his Morning Exerciſe, and being ſomthing long-winded, <hi>[And by the way it may be obſerved, that</hi>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:101712:21"/> 
               <hi>long Prayers proceeding from a Traiterous heart, once did good, but by accident onely]</hi> the Hoſtler, unwilling to loſe his reward at the Gentlemans taking horſe, returns with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doing his errand. As ſoon as my Lord was mounted and gone, <hi>Hamnet</hi> tells <hi>Weſtley</hi> of the diſcourſe between himſelf and the Hoſtler. Away comes <hi>Weſtley</hi> upon full ſpeed to the Inne, and (almoſt out of breath) asks the woman of the houſe, what Gueſts ſhe had entertained that night? She ſaid, They were all ſtrangers to her, ſhe knew them not. I tell you then (ſaid he) one of them was the King. Then haſtily turning away from her, he and <hi>Hamnet</hi> ran to <hi>Mr. Butler</hi> of <hi>Commer</hi> (then Juſtice of Peace) to have him diſpatch abroad his Warrants to raiſe the Country for the apprehending of the King, and thoſe perſons the laſt night with him at <hi>Charmouth.</hi> But he ſpends his mouth in vain, a deaf ear is turned upon him, no Warrant would be iſſued forth. This check given to his zeal ſo vexed him, that it had like to have cauſed a ſuffocation, had not Captain <hi>Maſſey</hi> (as errant a Hotſpur as himſelf) given it vent, by raiſing a Party
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:101712:21"/> and purſuing the King upon <hi>London-Road.</hi> But God preſerved his Majeſty by divert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him to <hi>Broadwindſor,</hi> whilſt <hi>Maſſey</hi> and his hot-mettled company outran their Prey as far as <hi>Dorcheſter.</hi> And indeed, the report of the Kings being at <hi>Charmouth,</hi> was grown ſo common, that the Soldiers (lying in thoſe parts) ſearch'd the houſes of ſeveral Gentlemen, who were accounted Royaliſts, thinking to ſurprize him. Amongſt which, <hi>Pileſdon</hi> (the houſe of Sir <hi>Hugh Wyndham</hi> Uncle to Colonel <hi>Francis Wyndham)</hi> was twice rifled. They took the old Baronet, his Lady, Daughters, and whole Family, and ſet a Guard upon them in the Hall, whilſt they examine every corner, not ſparing either Trunk or Box. Then taking a particular view of their Priſoners, they ſeize a lovely young Lady, ſaying, ſhe was the King diſguiſed in womens apparel. At length being convinced of their groſs and rude miſtake, they deſiſted from offering any farther violence to that Family. And here it is much to be obſerved, that the ſame day the King went from <hi>Charmouth,</hi> Captain <hi>Eleſden</hi> came to <hi>Pileſdon,</hi> and enquired of
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:101712:22"/> Sir <hi>Hugh</hi> and his Lady for the King and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonel, confidently affirming that they muſt needs be there.</p>
            <p>His Majeſty having with an evenneſs of ſpirit gotten through this rough paſſage, ſafely anchored at <hi>Broadwindſor:</hi> Where at length enjoying ſome reſt, he commands the Colonel to give his opinion what courſe was to be taken, as the face of affairs then looked. The Colonel (ſeeing Forces drawn every where upon that ſhore) thought it very hazardous to attempt any thing more in <hi>Dorſetſhire;</hi> and therefore humbly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſought his Majeſty, that he would be pleaſed to retreat to <hi>Trent:</hi> He hoped his Majeſty was already ſatisfied in the fidelity of his ſervants; and that he doubted not, his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty might lie ſecurely in that Creek, till it was fair weather, and a good ſeaſon to put forth to Sea. He humbly adviſed, that <hi>Peters</hi> might conduct the Lord <hi>Wilmot</hi> to <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Huit's</hi> houſe at the <hi>Kings-Arms</hi> in <hi>Sarum,</hi> where he and many of his friends had been ſheltered in the time of troubles. That <hi>Peters</hi> (being at <hi>Sarum)</hi> ſhould by a private token bring his Lordſhip to <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> John Coventry</hi> (his Kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man)
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:101712:22"/> a Perſon Noble, Wiſe, and Loyal, with whom he had kept Intelligence in order to the Kings ſervice, ever ſince his Majeſty had ſet foot in <hi>Scotland;</hi> That he was aſſured <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Coventry</hi> would think himſelf highly ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured to correſpond in this matchleſs em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment, <hi>The King's Preſervation.</hi> He de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired the Lord <hi>Wilmot</hi> to be confident of ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing concealed; And likewiſe to treat with <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Coventry,</hi> and by <hi>Peters</hi> to return his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty an account how he found that Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man affected towards this ſervice.</p>
            <p>This counſel being well reliſhed and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved, 'twas reſolved, That between <hi>Sarum</hi> and <hi>Trent</hi> (lying 30 miles diſtant and better) an Intercourſe ſhould be kept by truſty meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers, and a ſecret way of writing, to avoid danger in caſe of interception. All things being thus concluded, the King left his jovial Hoſt at <hi>Broadwindſor,</hi> and returned with the Colonel and <hi>M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Coningsby</hi> to <hi>Trent.</hi> The Lord <hi>Wilmot</hi> with <hi>Peters</hi> went that night to <hi>Sherborn,</hi> and the next morning was waited on by <hi>Swan</hi> (who attended his Lordſhip to the Colonels) and that day got into <hi>Sarum;</hi> where he ſoon ſaluted <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Coventry,</hi> in all
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:101712:23"/> things fully anſwering his Lordſhips expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: And (the 25. of <hi>September) Peters</hi> was ſent back with this joyful meſſage from the Lord <hi>Wilmot</hi> to his Majeſty, That he doubted not (by <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Coventry's</hi> aſſiſtance, and thoſe recommended by him) to be able in ſome ſhort time to effect his deſires.</p>
            <p>Whilſt his Sacred Majeſty enjoys his peace at <hi>Trent,</hi> and the Lord <hi>Wilmot</hi> (with thoſe other Worthies) is buſied at <hi>Sarum</hi> to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure its continuation, It cannot be imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent to mention a Circumſtance or two, which inſerted in the midſt of the web and texture of this Story would have looked un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>handſom, but added as a fringe may prove ornamental.</p>
            <p>Upon the Sunday morning after the King came to <hi>Trent,</hi> a Tailor of the Pariſh inform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Colonel, That the Zealots [which ſwarmed in that place] diſcourſed overnight, that Perſons of Quality were hid in his houſe, and that they intended to ſearch and ſeiſe them; and therefore he deſired the Colonel (if any ſuch there were) to convey them thence, to avoid ſurpriſal. The Colonel (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warding the good man for his care and kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:101712:23"/> towards himſelf and family) told him, That his Kinſman (meaning the <hi>L. Wilmot)</hi> was not private, but publick in his houſe, (for ſo his Lordſhip pleaſed to be) and that he believed he would ſhew himſelf in the Church at the time of Prayers. When the honeſt fellow was gone, the Colonel ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaints the King what had paſſed between himſelf and the Tailor, and withall beſought his Majeſty to perſwade the Lord <hi>Wilmot</hi> to accompany him to Church, thinking by this means not only to leſſen the jealouſie, but alſo to gain the good opinion of ſome of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naticks, who would be apt to believe, that the Colonel was rather brought to Church by my Lord, then his Lordſhip by the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonel, who ſeldom came to that Place, ſince Faction and Rebellion had juſtled out, and kept poſſeſſion againſt Peace and Religion. He alledged moreover, that he ſate in an Ile diſtinct from the body of the Congregation, ſo that the Pariſhioners could not take a full view of any of his company. Theſe reaſons, joined with his Majeſties command, prevailed with his Lordſhip; and (though he thought it a bold adventure, yet) it not only allayed the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:101712:24"/> fury, but alſo took out the very ſting of thoſe waſps; inſomuch that they who the laſt night talked of nothing but ſearching, began now to ſay, that <hi>Cromwell's</hi> late ſucceſs againſt the King, had made the Colonel a Convert.</p>
            <p>All being now quiet about home, the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonels Lady (under a pretence of a Viſit) goes over to <hi>Sherborn</hi> to hear what news there was abroad of the King. And towards evening, at her return, a Troop of horſe clapt private<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly into the town. This ſilent way of entring their Quarters, in ſo triumphant a time, gave a ſtrong alarm to this careful Lady, whoſe thoughts were much troubled concerning her Royal Gueſt. A ſtop ſhe made to hearken out what brought them thither, and whither they were bound: But not one grain of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence could be procured by the moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrious enquiry. When ſhe came home, ſhe gave his Majeſty an account of many ſtories, which like flying clouds were blown about by the breath of the people, ſtriving to cover her trouble with the vail of cheerfulneſs. But this the King perceiving to be rather forced then free, as at other times, was earneſt to know the cauſe of her diſcompoſure. And
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:101712:24"/> to ſatisfie his Majeſties importunity, ſhe gave him a full relation of the Troop at <hi>Sherborn:</hi> At which his Majeſty laughed moſt heartily, as if he had not been in the leaſt concerned. Yet up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a ſerious debate of the matter, the Colonel and his Lady ſupplicated the King to take a view of his Privy chamber, into which he was perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to enter, but came preſently forth again, much pleaſed, that upon the leaſt approach of danger, he could thither retreat with an aſſurance of ſecurity. All that night the Colonel kept ſtrict watch in his houſe, and was the more vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant, becauſe he underſtood from <hi>Sherborn,</hi> that the Troop intended not to quarter there, but only to refreſh themſelves and march. And ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly (not ſo much as looking towards <hi>Trent)</hi> about two of the clock next morning, they removed towards the Sea-coaſt. This fear being over, the King reſted all the time of his ſtay at <hi>Trent,</hi> without ſo much as the apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of a diſturbance.</p>
            <p>The ſtrangeneſs of which will be much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed by the addition of what a Captain who ſerved under <hi>Cromwell</hi> at <hi>Worceſter,</hi> reported to two Divines of undoubted veracity, long before the King's bleſſed Reſtauration: That he was followed and troubled with Dreams for three
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:101712:25"/> nights together, That the King was hid at <hi>Trent</hi> near <hi>Sherborn,</hi> in a houſe nigh to which ſtood a Grove or patch of trees, and that thither he ſhould go and find him. This ſuggeſtion thus reiterated, was a powerful ſpur to prick him for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards: But the hand which held the reins and kept him back, was irreſiſtible.</p>
            <p>Now the hands of his Majeſties enemies were not only reſtrained from doing him evil, but the hands of his friends were ſtrengthened to do him good. In order to which, Colonel <hi>Eward Phe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lips</hi> of <hi>Montacute</hi> in the County of <hi>Somerſet,</hi> came from <hi>Sarum</hi> to his Majeſty <hi>(Septemb.</hi> 28.) with this intelligence, That his brother Colonel <hi>Robert Phelips</hi> was employed to <hi>Southampton</hi> to procure a Veſſel, of whoſe tranſaction his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty ſhould receive a ſpeedy account.</p>
            <p>In the mean time, Captain <hi>Thomas Littleton</hi> (a Neighbour of Colonel <hi>Wyndham)</hi> was diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch'd up into <hi>Hampſhire,</hi> where by the aid of <hi>Mr. Standiſh</hi> he dealt with the Maſter of a Ship, who undertook to carry off the Lord <hi>Wilmot</hi> and his company, upon the condition his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip would follow his direction. But the hope of Colonel <hi>Phelips</hi> his good ſucceſs at <hi>Hampton</hi> daſh'd this enterpriſe, and the Captain was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to <hi>Trent,</hi> and to make no progreſs till farther order.</p>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:101712:25"/>
            <p> Upon the firſt of <hi>October, Mr. John Sellick</hi> (Chaplain to <hi>Mr. Coventry)</hi> brought a Letter to his Majeſty. In anſwer to which the King wrote back, That he deſired all diligence might be uſed in providing a Veſſel; and if it ſhould prove difficult at <hi>Hampton,</hi> trial ſhould be made farther: That they ſhould be aſcertained of a Ship before they ſent to remove him, that ſo he might run no more hazards then what of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity he muſt meet with in his paſſage from <hi>Trent</hi> to the place of his Tranſportation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>October</hi> the fifth, Colonel <hi>Phelips</hi> came from the Lord <hi>Wilmot</hi> and <hi>Mr. Coventry</hi> to his Majeſty with this aſſurance, That all things were ready; And that he had informed himſelf with the moſt private ways, that ſo he might with greater probability of ſafety guide his Majeſty to the Sea-ſide. Aſſoon as the King heard this meſſage, He reſolved upon his Journey. Colonel <hi>Wynd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> earneſtly petitions his Majeſty, that he might wait on him to the ſhore: But his Majeſty gave no grant, ſaying, It was no way neceſſary, and might prove very inconvenient. Upon the renewing his requeſt, the King commanded the contrary, but ſweetned his denial with this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, That if he were put to any diſtreſs, he would again retreat to <hi>Trent.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:101712:26"/>
            <p> About ten next morning <hi>(October</hi> the ſixth) his Majeſty took leave of the old Lady <hi>Wynd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> the Colonels Lady and Family; not omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the meaneſt of them that ſerved him. But to the good old Lady he vouchſafed more then an ordinary reſpect, who accounted it her higheſt honour, that ſhe had three Sons and one Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>child ſlain in the defence of the Father, and that ſhe her ſelf in her old age had been inſtrumental in the protection of the Son, Both Kings of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus his Sacred Majeſty, taking <hi>M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Juliana Coningsby</hi> behind him, attended by Colonel <hi>Robert Phelips,</hi> and <hi>Peters,</hi> bade Farewel to <hi>Trent,</hi> the Ark in which God ſhut him up, when the Floods of Rebellion had covered the face of his Dominions. Here he reſted Nine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen days, to give his faithful Servants time to work his deliverance: And the Almighty crowned their endeavours with ſucceſs, that his Majeſty might live to appear as Glorious in his Actions, as Couragious in his Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:101712:26"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
